- I'm joined
Speaker 1: now by Democratic Senator Jeff Merkley, Democrat from Oregon who formerly worked as a national security analyst at the Pentagon. Your reaction to the president today, there were a lot of folks who really felt like they wanted him to be more vociferous, to be more pointed, to maybe call out Donald Trump for his sort of refusal to accept the intelligence community consensus. What
Speaker 2: was your
reaction?
Well,
Speaker 3: we have to recognize that this is the political equivalent of 9-11. Russia has attacked the core process in our nation, the
Speaker 4: core process behind our presidency. And this is not just a modest deal or a big deal. This is a gigantic issue, and it deserves massive exploration, declassification. The Americans need to know the story. We have to develop a strategy for it to never happen again. And when you're done
Speaker 4: understand the full depth of it. For example, the New York Times has reported that it's not just Russia hacking to influence the presidential election, but to also influence congressional elections. So a bipartisan independent commission
Speaker 5: similar to that for 9-11 is absolutely essential. So on
Speaker 6: that policy ground, the
Speaker 1: president called for that. Dick Durbin has been on this program calling for that. Ben Cardin has called for it. Others have as well. You're of the belief that should happen. But I can't help but notice that your tone about this is very different than the presidents.
Speaker 1: The president took pain today to kind of tamp down the rhetoric about
Speaker 7: this, basically saying we hold our own destiny in our hands, and if our political culture weren't as bad as it
Speaker 8: is and if the media weren't as bad as it is, we wouldn't be here. You're calling this the political equivalent of 9/11, who's right?
Well,
Speaker 9: certainly I feel
Speaker 5: like the President feels a responsibility to have a gracious
Speaker 4: transition of power. He feels that's his role at the moment. But our role is to recognize that our political system has been hacked by a hostile foreign power and that that is a huge issue. It compromises the legitimacy of the presidency coming in. We have a President-elect who lost the citizens' election and now we find out a lot of the
Speaker 4: These very narrow votes in key states were influenced by a Russian operation. And that is completely unacceptable. So we've really got to go out this with a lot of vigor. What's missing in the puzzle are the Republicans setting up and we really need to have this bipartisan commission. Imagine the situation if it was reversed. FBI found out in September 2015 that the DNC was being hacked and they didn't go brief the DNC. Can you imagine if that was a Republican?
Speaker 4: national committee that was hacked and the FBI didn't fill them in, they would be up in arms. We've got to walk in each other's shoes here. This is just an unacceptable assault.
So
Speaker 10: in terms of walking in each other's shoes, I want to be specific here. You mentioned the narrow margin, and I assume you mean across the three states to determine the election,
Speaker 7: 80,000 votes. You know, we don't have any specific causal evidence, right, that the leaks themselves produce the outcome. Do you believe they were definitive?
Well, I
Speaker 5: wouldn't go as far as to say definitive because there were many elements in those final days, including the actions of our director of the FBI. I must say that the director of the FBI, between not briefing the DNC about the Russian hacking and then interfering 11 days before the election, has proven himself really in history. He'll be one of the worst
Speaker 11: directors we've ever had. This is just an outrageous performance by the FBI. What
Speaker 12: do you say to folks, Sean Spicer, Kellyanne Conway, other Republicans, who basically say
Speaker 1: you, Senator,
Speaker 1: of sour grapes,
Speaker 7: you're being a sore loser, and you're attempting to undermine legitimacy of the duly elected incoming president-elect of the United States. I would
say that if
Speaker 5: you're a patriotic American, you care when America is attacked. And attacking the validity of our elections goes right to the heart of who we are. So let's stand together, let's take on this threat, let's fully explore it, let's fully understand it. And it does cast
a cloud over the
Speaker 5: incoming administration, but that's because of the facts. And it's the facts of the situation, it's not political positioning that casts that cloud. All right,
Speaker 2: Senator Jeff Merkley, thanks for your time, I appreciate it. You're
Speaker 5: welcome.